Guide to the Donald M. Goldstein Collection, 1886-2005 UA.90.F78
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Donald M. Goldstein Collection
1886-2005
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Goldstein, Donald M.
UA.90.F78
114.75 Linear Feet (72 manuscript boxes, 12 photograph boxes, 4 oversize boxes, 8 record center boxes)
This collection contains the professional papers of Donald M. Goldstein (1932-2017 ), an historian of the Pacific theater of World War II and professor at the University of Pittsburgh. The crux of this collection is the World War II series. It contains invaluable primary documentation, the bulk of which is unique to this collection and consists of interviews and personal papers from the military leaders and government officials involved in the Pearl Harbor attack. In addition to the World War II series, this collection highlights Goldstein's other research interests: Amelia Earhart, International Relations, Korean War, Spanish-American War, Vietnam War, Ennis Whitehead, Williwaw War, World War I and Jacob Deshazer. Largely composed of textual documents such as correspondence, diaries, financial records, interview transcripts, manuscripts, notes, publications, reports, and subject files; this collection benefits from an exhaustive collection of photographs.
Biography
Donald M. Goldstein (1932-2017) was a retired U.S. Air Force lieutenant colonel and best-selling author, who dedicated over thirty years to teaching at the University of Pittsburgh's Graduate School of International Affairs (GSPIA). A well-respected professor, Goldstein received numerous awards such as the Excellence in Teaching Award from the National Association of Schools of Public Affairs and Administration in 1999 and the Chancellor's Distinguished Teaching Award in 2001. Acting as either the author or co-author, Goldstein published over twenty books. His best sellers, At Dawn We Slept: The Untold Story of Pearl Harbor and Miracle at Midway, have obtained international acclaim and are printed in several languages. Over the years, Goldstein emerged as an authority on the Pacific theater of World War II. As such, he participated in hundreds of speaking engagements and consulted for numerous television news programs. Most significantly, Goldstein received two George Foster Peabody awards for his contributions to the ABC specials "Pearl Harbor: Two Hours that Changed the World" and "D-Day: A Soldier's Story."
Donald M. Goldstein was born on December 15, 1932 in New York City, New York. He studied history at the University of Maryland where he received a B.A. in 1954 and a M.A. in 1962. In 1963 he received a M.S. in political science from Georgetown University, and a M.S. in public administration from George Washington University in 1965. In 1970, Goldstein received a PhD in history from Denver University. He also graduated from the Squadron Officer School, the U.S. Air Force Air Command and Staff College Resident Program, and the Air War College Nonresident Program.
Spanning over 40 years, Goldstein's professional career in academia covered a variety of topics such as U.S. history, military history, arms control, international security, international relations, and foreign policy process. Prior to joining the University of Pittsburgh, Goldstein worked in the history department of several institutions including the University of Tampa, United States Air Force Academy, and Troy State University. Since the fall of 1974, Goldstein was associated with the Graduate School of Public and International Affairs (GSPIA) at the University of Pittsburgh. During this time, Goldstein held several administrative positions and became a tenured full professor in 1992. A favorite among his students and co-workers at GSPIA, Goldstein received fourteen awards as either the Teacher of the Year or Outstanding Teacher between the years 1987-2006.
In addition to his teaching career, Goldstein was an accomplished editor and author. He published a multitude of World War II books that are based upon the research of his mentor Gordon Prange (1910–1980), including several best sellers. In addition to the World War II books, Goldstein published other manuscripts, including a biography of Amelia Earhart, an international relations text book, and eight pictorial books on the United States' participation in foreign conflicts. Goldstein wrote a military history of the United States published in 2007, and a biography of World War II pilot Jacob Desazer, which was published in 2010.
Goldstein was married to Mariann, a retired nurse practitioner from University of Pittsburgh Medical Center, with whom he had four children and six grandchildren. Goldstein passed away on December 17, 2017.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 16 series, loosely grouped by topic. Extensive scope and content notes are provided at the following series levels:
Series I. Amelia Earhart
Series II. International Relations
Series III. Korea
Series IV. Spanish American War
Series V. Vietnam War
Series VI. Ennis Whitehead
Series VII. Williwaw War
Series VIII. World War I
Series IX. World War II
Series X. Prange Enterprise
Series XI. Personal, Donald Goldstein
Series XII. Academic Career and Course Materials
Series XIII. Photographs
Series XIV. Oversized Materials
Series XV. 2012 Additions
Series XVI. 2013 Additions
Scope and Content Notes
This collection documents Donald M. Goldstein's professional pursuits in researching, writing and teaching from the 1970s through 2005, and consists of correspondence, contracts, course materials, diaries, financial records, manuscripts, notes, photographs, publications, reference files, reports, transcripts, and videos. The first nine series represent Goldstein's primary research interests, which resulted in publications about Amelia Earhart, International Relations, Korean War, Spanish-American War, Vietnam War, Williwaw War, Ennis Whitehead, World War I and World War II. Of these series, World War II is the most significant, as it contains valuable primary documentation gathered directly from World War II participants and archival institutions located throughout Japan and the United States. In general, these resources provide first-hand accounts of the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor and the resulting Pacific War from the perspective of military commanders, political leaders, and enlisted men. The World War II series also contains substantial documentation on the D-Day Invasion of Normandy, and the Battle of the Bulge in the Ardennes. In addition to the research files, the first nine series also contain manuscripts and related materials that document the process of writing manuscripts, editing drafts, creating page proofs, and marketing the final product. This entire process requires a constant flow of communication that is documented through correspondence, lists of corrections, and revised manuscript drafts. The remaining series detail Goldstein's personal interests, his affiliation with Prange Enterprises, and his teaching career, as well as the photographic and oversized materials that give some depth to this largely textual collection.
Two additional series, processed in 2012 and 2013, respectively, consists of correspondence, newspaper clippings, publications, images and manuscript materials for a biography about Jacob Deshazer, a former Doolittle Raider.
Access Restrictions
The student papers are restricted. A signed confidentiality agreement is required for access.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Donald M. Goldstein on March 12, 2006.
Custodial History
The bulk of the World War II research files were originally amassed by Gordon W. Prange. During his tenure with General Douglas MacArthur's Historical Division from 1942 to 1951, Prange collected primary documentation from and interviewed World War II-era officials in Japan. Over the next twenty years, Prange and his assistant, Katherine V. Dillon, contacted American veterans and frequented archival institutions to develop the American perspective. During this period, Prange began his four-volume study of the Pearl Harbor attack, "Tora, Tora Tora," as well as several related projects such as the diary of Matome Ugaki, an analysis of the Battle of Midway, and biographies of Mitsuo Fuchida and Richard Sorge. With his health declining, Prange contacted Donald M. Goldstein to complete the necessary revisions and negotiate with publishers to ensure the publication of his books. Upon his death in 1980, Prange's files were transferred to his research assistant Katherine V. Dillon and his protégé Donald M. Goldstein. Goldstein received the remainder of Prange's files from Katherine V. Dillon upon her death.
Previous Citation
Donald M. Goldstein Collection, 1886-2005, UA.90.F78, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Existence and Location of Originals
This collection contains manuscript materials photocopied from the Library of Congress, National Archives, University of Wyoming, Franklin D. Roosevelt Library, Naval Historical Center, Hoover Institute on War, and additional archival institutions. It also includes reprints of images from the National Archives, Smithsonian Institute, Army War College, U.S. Naval Institute, German Bundesarchive, and similar institutions. The agencies of origination are documented within the files.
Related Material
Additional information about Gordon Prange can be found at the University of Maryland.
Papers of Gordon Prange, 1920-1980, (unprocessed)
The Gordon W. Prange Collection, 1945-1949, www.lib.umd.edu/prange/index.jsp
Separated Material
Books noted in this finding aid are catalogued and stored separately. For preservation purposes, the photographs are stored separately in the media room. The oversized materials are also stored separately.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Pacific Ocean; Battle of Midway, 1942; Pearl Harbor (Hawaii), Attack on, 1941; World War, 1939-1945; University of Pittsburgh; Faculty papers; International relations; Korean War, 1950-1953; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Alaska -- Aleutian Islands; World War, 1939-1945 -- Naval operations, Japanese; Earhart, Amelia; Fuchida, Mitsuo; Goldstein, Donald M.; Prange, Gordon W. (Gordon William); Sorge, Richard; Ugaki, Matome; Whitehead, Ennis Clement; Sell, Oliver M.
- Amelia Earhart, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The files in this series date from 1928 to 2002 and contain Donald Goldstein's research files and manuscript drafts based upon Amelia Earhart's aviation career and her mysterious disappearance in 1937. Researchers should refer to Series XIII: Photographs to view images of Earhart. The files are further described in the following subseries scope notes.
  - Research Materials, 1.
    This subseries contains the research materials gathered by Donald Goldstein as he investigated Amelia Earhart's aviation career and disappearance. Although limited in quantity, the Earhart disappearance correspondence, documentary evidence file, Federal Bureau of Investigation files, and radio logs chronicle the actions of Earhart's contemporaries to track and locate the missing aviator. This primary research is supplemented by secondary sources such as articles, newspaper clippings and manuscripts. In addition to his research, Goldstein received several files from John Luttrell, a prolific theorist on the disappearance of Earhart. The Luttrell correspondence and related documents, all copies copies of the originals, examine various theories of Earhart's disappearance, as well as possible locations for her crash site. The files are arranged alphabetically by record type.
    - Articles
      - Earhart Disappearance, 1966 - 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 1978 - 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Tokyo Rose, 1983 - 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bibliographies
      - Bibliographies, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence
      - Earhart Disappearance, 1937 - 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Gervais, Joe, 1965 - 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Luttrell, John (copies), 1985 - 1988 (Box 1, Folder 7-10)
      - Safford, Laurence, 1971 - 1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Documentary Evidence
      - Documentary Evidence Collected by Safford, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - FBI Files
      - Earhart, Amelia, 1937 - 1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Putnam, George P., 1937 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Rothar, Wilbur, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Manuscripts
      - 20 HRS. 40 MINS. by Amelia Earhart, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Courage is the Price: A Biography of Amelia Earhart, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - The Earhart Disappearance. The British Connection, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Eyewitness: The Amelia Earhart Incident, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - The Fun of It by Amelia Earhart, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Get Underway - Eyewitness Accounts, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Hollywood Pilot: A Biography of Paul Mantz, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Last Flight by Amelia Earhart, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Letters from Amelia Earhart, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous Excerpts, 1938 - 1987 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
      - My search for Amelia…Alive!, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Soaring Wings: A Biography of Amelia Earhart, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Untitled, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Soaring Wings: A Biography of Amelia Earhart, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - World Flight: The Earhart Trail, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Maps
      - Hand-Drawn Maps and Calculations of Possible Crash Site, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Information on Locating and Acquiring Maps, 1985 - 1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1935 - 1986
      - Miscellaneous material, 1935 - 1986 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Newspaper Clippings
      - Autogyro Altitude Record, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Earhart Aviation Career, 1929 - 1936 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Scrapbook of Articles on Earhart, 1937 - 1986 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Theories on Disappearance and Remembrance, 1937 - 1997 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
      - Nihau Island, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Radio Logs, July 1937
      - Radio Logs, July 1937 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Subject Files
      - Aero Philatelic Federation of the Americas, 1978 - 1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Earhart Birth Centennial Celebration, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Japanese Search for Earhart, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Pacific Islands, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Paxton, Nina, 1944 - 1986 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Weather and Currents, 1977 - 1986 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Manuscripts and Related Materials, 2.
    The manuscript drafts in this subseries document the development of the biography from the original drafts of Flight Into Yesterday through its evolution into Amelia: The Centennial Biography of an Aviation Pioneer. While the earliest drafts concentrate on the technical aspects of Earhart's flight, the later drafts provide an expanded portrait of Earhart and document both her childhood and development as an aviator. In addition to manuscripts, this subseries contains corrections and correspondence generated by Goldstein while writing and promoting the biography, which was eventually published in 1997.
    - Corrections, 1996 - 1997 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence- General, 1987 - 2002 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
    - Correspondence- Luttrell, John, 1986 - 1996 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Manuscript Drafts, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-24)
    - Manuscript Drafts, undated (Box 4, Folder 1-14)
    - Manuscript Drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 1-15)
- International Relations, II.
  The files in this series date from 1990-2005 and contain the manuscript drafts and related materials utilized by Donald Goldstein and his associates in their compilation of several international relations books. The manuscript drafts consist of introductions to articles, edited source materials, and page proofs for Classic Readings of International Relations (1994 and 1998), Classic Readings and Contemporary Debates in International Relations (2005), as well as the unpublished manuscript drafts of several essays. The drafts are augmented by correspondence which focuses on editing the text and obtaining permission for the reproduction of essays. Files are arranged alphabetically by manuscript title. Researchers should refer to Series XIII: Photographs to view images either considered for or used in the publication of The Dictionary of Twentieth Century World Politics and HarperCollins Dictionary of American Government and Politics.
  - Copyright Permissions, 1992 - 1993 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1990 - 2005 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript Drafts of 1st Edition, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 3-16)
  - Research Materials, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Manuscript Drafts of 2nd Edition, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 18-23)
  - Manuscript Drafts of 2nd Edition, 1998 - 1999 (Box 7, Folder 1-9)
  - Manuscript Drafts of 3rd Edition, 2004 - 2005 (Box 7, Folder 10-22)
  - Manuscript Drafts of Dictionary of World Politics, June 1992 (Box 7, Folder 23-27)
  - Manuscript Drafts of Dictionary of World Politics, June 1992 (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
- Korea, III.
  The files in this series date from 1946 to 1991 and contain Donald Goldstein's correspondence, manuscript drafts, and reference materials on Korea and the Korean War (1950-1953). The first subseries explores the creation of the pictorial, The Korean War: The Story and the Photographs. The second subseries contains files regarding General Matthew B. Ridgway, especially his command of United Nations troops in Korea. The third subseries, Security in Korea: War, Stalemate, and Negotiation, is a collection of articles with an historical perspective on Korea during the Cold War and its relations with the United States. The series are further described in the subseries scope notes.
  - The Korean War: The Story and the Photographs, 1.
    The Korean War: The Story and the Photographs, 1946-1999 This subseries documents the process of compiling the images and writing the narrative for The Korean War: The Story and the Photographs. Published in 2000 by Donald Goldstein and Harry J. Maihafer, this pictorial emphasizes the American forces' contribution during the conflict. The files mainly consist of manuscript drafts that are arranged chronologically and depict the development of the manuscript from the original draft to the published version. Images from this pictorial are contained and described in Series XIII: Photographs.
    - Correspondence, 1999 - 2000 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Captions, c. 1999 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Manuscript Drafts, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 7-9)
    - Research, 1945 - 1991 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - General Matthew B. Ridgway, 2.
    This subseries contains Goldstein's manuscript drafts and research materials concerning General Matthew B. Ridgway, particularly his command of the 8th Army in Korea, and the Allied Forces in the Far East. The manuscript drafts consist of a speech, an additional paper entitled "Douglas MacArthur-Matthew Ridgeway and the Korean War," and related documents. In addition to describing Ridgway's military career, the research files also highlight his post retirement activities. Images of Ridgway are located in Series XIII: Photographs.
    - Manuscript Drafts, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 11-13)
    - Research Materials- General Douglas MacArthur, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Research Materials- General Matthew Ridgway, 1952 - 2004 (Box 8, Folder 15-17)
    - Video - Ridgway Family News and Symposium, 1997
  - Security in Korea: War, Stalemate, and Negotiation, 3.
    This subseries documents the efforts of Donald Goldstein, Phil Williams, and Henry L. Andrews Jr. to publish Security in Korea: War, Stalemate, and Negotiation. Released in 1994, this book contains a collection of articles with an historical perspective of Cold War Korea and the state of U.S.-Korea relations.
    - Correspondence, 1991 - 1993 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Manuscript Drafts, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 19-21)
- Spanish American War, IV.
  The files in this series date from 1997 to 1998 and document Donald Goldstein's efforts to compile images and write the narrative for the Spanish-American War: The Story and Photographs. Published with the assistance of Katherine V. Dillon, J. Michael Wenger, and Robert J. Cressman, this pictorial provides brief sections on the events leading up to the Spanish-American War (1898) and the aftermath, with more detail devoted to the American perspective of the War and the prolonged peace process. The majority of the files consist of manuscript drafts that are arranged chronologically and expose the development of the manuscript from the original draft to the published version. Images from this pictorial are located in Series XIII: Photographs.
  - Corrections, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1996 - 1997 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript Drafts, 1996 - 1997 (Box 9, Folder 3-23)
  - Manuscripts Drafts, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 1-8)
- Vietnam War, V.
  The materials in this series date from 1993 to 1997 and document the process of compiling the images and writing the narrative for The Vietnam War: The Story and the Photographs by Donald Goldstein, Katherine V. Dillon, and J. Michael Wenger. Published in 1997, the pictorial centers on U.S. actions in Vietnam (1959-1975) with a brief overview of the following: the events before the direct involvement of the U.S., the protests in the U.S., and the aftermath of the war. The bulk of the documents are manuscript drafts, which chronicle the development of the manuscript from the original draft to the published version. Images from this pictorial are contained and described in Series XIII: Photographs.
  - Correspondence, 1994 - 2002 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript Drafts, 1995 - 1997 (Box 10, Folder 10-18)
  - Research Materials, 1975 - 1996 (Box 10, Folder 19-20)
- Ennis Whitehead, VI.
  This series dates from 1918 to 1994 and contains Donald Goldstein's research files and manuscript drafts for his 1970 doctorial dissertation Ennis C. Whitehead, Aerospace Commander and Pioneer, and a subsequent essay. The dissertation traces Whitehead's entire military career from his service as a World War I test pilot through his retirement as head of the Air Defense Command in 1951. The essay examines Whitehead's leadership of the Allied Forces in the South Pacific during World War II. Researchers interested in viewing images of Whitehead should consult Series XIII: Photographs. These records are further described in the following subseries scope notes.
  - Research Materials, 1.
    While these files offer very little insight into Ennis Whitehead's personal life, they create an excellent portrait of his entire military career with the United States Army Air Corps and Air Force. Dating from 1918-1967, the Whitehead correspondence is especially noteworthy, as it contains his official military correspondence with various military commanders, and his private letters to family members. His military career is further illuminated through flight logs, maps, memoranda, military histories, newspaper clippings, and subject files. The files are arranged alphabetically by record type.
    - Article, 1927 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence- 5th Bomber Command Headquarters, 1944 - 1945 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence- Smith, General Frederick, 1964 - 1967 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Ennis Whitehead Correspondence- General, 1922 - 1965 (Box 11, Folder 4-31)
    - Ennis Whitehead Correspondence- General, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Ennis Whitehead Correspondence- Alison, John, 1956 - 1963 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Ennis Whitehead Correspondence- Kenney, George, 1943 - 1951 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Ennis Whitehead Correspondence- Military Orders, 1918 - 1951 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Ennis Whitehead Correspondence- Pan American Flight, 1926 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Ennis Whitehead Correspondence- Personal, 1918 - 1965 (Box 12, Folder 6-12)